Do you ever stop and think, during a romantic dinner,
在进行浪漫晚餐的时候， 你们有没有停下来想想，
"I've just left my fingerprints all over my wine glass."
“我刚在红酒杯上留满了指纹”。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
Or do you ever worry, when you visit a friend,
或者你有没有担心，当你拜访朋友时，
about leaving a little piece of you behind on every surface that you touch?
在每一个触碰中留下的那一丝痕迹？
And even this evening,
即便今天晚上，
have you paid any attention to sit without touching anything?
你们坐下时有没有留意不触碰任何东西？
Well, you're not alone.
好吧，并不只是你们如此。
Thankfully, criminals underestimate the power of fingerprints, too.
谢天谢地，犯罪分子也低估了指纹的力量。
And I'm not just talking about the twisted parting of lines
我说的可不只是那一条条让我们的指纹
that make our fingerprint unique.
独一无二的扭曲线条。
I'm talking about an entire world of information
我谈论的是整个隐藏在
hiding in a small, often invisible thing.
微小，常常不可见的物体中的信息世界。
In fact, fingerprints are made up of molecules
事实上，组成指纹的分子
that belong to three classes:
可以分为三大类：
sweat molecules that we all produce in very different amounts ...
我们产生的数量非常不同的汗液分子…
molecules that we introduce into our body and then we sweat out
进入我们体内然后排出去的分子
and molecules that we may contaminate our fingertips with
和污染我们指尖的分子，
when we come across substances like blood, paint, grease,
在我们遇到像血液，油漆，油脂那样的物质时，
but also invisible substances.
但也有不可见的物质。
And molecules are the storytellers of who we are
分子是我们是谁
and what we've been up to.
和我们一直所从事的事的说书人。
We just need to have the right technology to make them talk.
我们只是需要有合适技术让它们开口说话。
So let me take you on a journey of unthinkable capabilities.
所以，让我带你们踏上这段 不可思议的能力之旅。
Katie has been raped
凯蒂被强奸了，
and her lifeless body has been found in the woods three days later,
她的尸体在她失踪后的三天
after her disappearance.
在树林里被发现。
The police is targeting three suspects,
警方锁定了三个嫌疑人，
having narrowed down the search from over 20 men
已从案发当天被目击路过那片区域的
who had been seen in that area on the same day.
超过20人中缩减而来。
The only piece of evidence
唯一的证据
is two very faint, overlapping fingerprints
是缠在凯蒂脖子的带子上面
on the tape that was found wrapped around Katie's neck.
发现的两个非常模糊的、重叠的指纹。
Often, faint and overlapping fingerprints cannot help the police
通常情况下，模糊和重叠的指纹对警方鉴定
to make an identification.
没有帮助。
And until recently, this might have been the end of the road,
直至最近，这可能还是走不通，
but this is where we can make the difference.
但这是我们可以发挥作用的地方。
The tape is sent to our labs,
带子送到了我们实验室，
where we're asked to use our cutting-edge technology
我们被要求使用最尖端技术
to help with the investigation.
来帮助调查。
And here, we use an existing form
在这里，我们使用了一种
of mass spectrometry imaging technology
现成的质谱成像技术，
that we have further developed and adapted
我们已经专门针对指纹的
specifically for the molecular and imaging analysis of fingerprints.
分子和成像分析做了进一步的开发和适配。
In essence, we fire a UV laser at the print,
原理上，我们朝指纹发射一束紫外激光，
and we cause the desorption of the molecules from the print,
去引发指纹上的分子解吸，
ready to be captured by the mass spectrometer.
为被质谱仪捕获做好准备。
Mass spectrometry measures the weight of the molecules --
质谱法测量分子的重量——
or as we say, the mass --
或者如我们所说，质量——
and those numbers that you see there, they indicate that mass.
你看到的这些数字，它们表示质量。
But more crucially,
但更关键的是，
they indicate who those molecules are --
它们表示这些分子是谁——
whether I'm seeing paracetamol
我看到的是对乙酰氨基酚
or something more sinister, forensically speaking.
或是从法医证物角度来说更罪恶的东西。
We applied this technology to the evidence that we have
我们对证物采用这个技术
and we found the presence of condom lubricants.
并从中发现了避孕套的润滑剂。
In fact, we've developed protocols that enable us to even suggest
事实上，我们开发了一套流程让我们甚至可以知道
what brand of condom might have been used.
使用什么牌子的避孕套。
So we pass this information to the police,
于是我们把这个信息传达给警方，
who, meanwhile, have obtained a search warrant
警方，同时已经取得了搜查证
and they found the same brand of condom in Dalton's premises.
并在道尔顿的房子里发现了 同样牌子的避孕套。
And with Dalton and Thomson also having records for sexual assaults,
鉴于道尔顿和汤姆森也有性侵犯的记录，
then it is Chapman that may become the less likely suspect.
那么，查普曼就不太可能成为嫌疑人。
But is this information enough to make an arrest?
但这个信息足够去逮捕人了吗？
Of course not,
当然不够，
and we are asked to delve deeper with our investigation.
我们被要求深入我们的调查。
So we found out, also, the presence of other two very interesting molecules.
于是我们也发现了另外两个 非常有趣的分子的存在。
One is an antidepressant,
一种是抗抑郁药，
and one is a very special molecule.
另一种是非常特殊的分子。
It only forms in your body
如果你同时喝酒和吸食可卡因，
if you drink alcohol and consume cocaine at the same time.
只会在你的身体中形成。
And alcohol is known to potentiate the effects of cocaine,
众所周知，酒精会增强可卡因的作用，
so here, we now have a hint on the state of mind
所以在这，我们现在有了一个
of the individual whilst perpetrating the crime.
关于个人心理状态的提示。
We passed this information to the police,
我们把信息传递给警方，
and they found out that, actually, Thomson is a drug addict,
他们发现，事实上汤姆森是个瘾君子，
and he also has a medical record for psychotic episodes,
而且他也有精神病发的医疗记录，
for which presumably the antidepressant was prescribed.
大概是用抗抑郁药开的处方。
So now Thomson becomes the more likely suspect.
所以现在汤姆森成为了更有可能的嫌疑人。
But the reality is that I still don't know where these molecules are coming from,
但事实是，我仍然不知道 这些分子是从哪里来的，
from which fingerprint,
来自谁的指纹，
and who those two fingerprints belong to.
这两个指纹属于谁的。
Fear not.
不要害怕。
Mass spectrometry imaging can help us further.
质谱成像可以帮助我们更进一步。
In fact, the technology is so powerful
事实上，这个技术是如此强大
that we can see where these molecules are on a fingerprint.
我们可以看到这些分子在指纹上的位置。
Like you see in this video,
如这个视频中所看到，
every single one of those peaks corresponds to a mass,
每一个波峰都对应一个质量，
every mass to a molecule,
每一个质量对应一个分子，
and we can interrogate the software, by selecting each of those molecules,
我们可以通过选择每一个分子，并查询这个软件，
as to where they are present on a fingermark.
来了解它们在一个手指上的位置。
And some images are not very revealing,
有些照片不能说明问题，
some are better,
有些更好些，
some are really good.
有些真的很好。
And we can create multiple images of the same mark --
我们可以创建相同标记的多个图像——
in theory, hundreds of images of the same fingerprint --
理论上，对于我们检测到的很多分子，
for as many of the molecules that we have detected.
可以创建同个指纹的上百张图像。
So step one ...
所以步骤1…
for overlapping fingerprints, chances are,
对于重叠的指纹，很大可能性是，
especially if they come from different individuals,
特别是如果它们来自不同的个体，
that the molecular composition is not identical,
分子组成是不一样的，
so let's ask the software to visualize those unique molecules
让我们让软件来可视化这些
just present in one fingermark and not in the other one.
只在一个手指上，而不在 另一个手指上的独特分子。
By doing so,
这样做，
that's how we can separate the two ridge patterns.
这就是我们如何分离这两种嵴线类型的方法。
And this is really important
这真是非常重要，
because the police now are able to identify one of the two fingerprints,
因为警察现在就可以鉴定两个指纹中的一个，
which actually corresponds to Katie.
其中正好和凯蒂的是相对应的。
And they've been able to say so
他们现在可以这样说
because they've compared the two separate images
是因为他们把这两张分开的图片
with one taken posthumously from Katie.
跟死后的凯蒂上拍到的做了对比。
So now, we can concentrate on one fingerprint only --
所以现在，我们可以聚焦在只有一个指纹上了——
that of the killer's.
属于凶手的。
So then, step two ...
然后，步骤2…
where are these three molecules that I've seen?
我所见过的这三个分子在哪里？
Well, let's interrogate the software -- show me where they are.
好吧，让我们来查一下软件—— 告诉我它们在哪里。
And by doing this,
通过这样做，
only portions of the image of the killer's fingerprint show up.
只有凶手的部分指纹出现了。
In other words,
换句话说，
those substances are only present in the killer's print.
这些物质只存在于凶手的指纹中。
So now our molecular findings start matching very nicely
所以现在我们的分子发现开始很好地匹配
the police intelligence about Thomson,
警察掌握的关于汤姆森的情报，
should that fingerprint belong to him.
那指纹应该属于他。
But the reality is that that print is still not good enough
但事实是这个指纹仍然不够好
to make an identification.
去做鉴定。
Step three:
步骤3:
since we can generate hundreds of images of the same fingerprint,
既然我们可以生成数百张相同指纹的图像，
why don't we superimpose them,
我们为什么不把它们叠加起来呢，
and by doing so,
通过这样做，
try to improve the rich pattern of continuity and clarity?
试着改善连续性和清晰性的丰富模式。
That's the result.
这就是结果。
Striking.
非常惊人。
We now have a very clear image of the fingerprint
我们现在有了指纹的清晰图像，
and the police can run it through the database.
警察已经可以在数据库中检索了。
The match comes out to Thomson.
匹配结果显示是汤姆森。
Thomson is our killer.
汤姆森就是凶手。
(Applause)
（鼓掌）
Katie, the suspects and the circumstances of the crime aren't real,
凯蒂、犯罪嫌疑人和犯罪现场都不是真实的，
but the story contains elements
但这个故事包含了
of the real police casework we've been confronted with,
我们所遇到的真正的警察案件的元素，
and is a composite of the intelligence that we can provide --
而这也包含了我们所能提供给警察的
that we have been able to provide the police.
情报信息的组合。
And I'm really, really thrilled that after nine years of intense research,
在9年的深入研究后，我真的真的非常激动，
as of 2017,
在2017年，
we are able to contribute to police investigations.
我们能够对警方的调查做出贡献。
Mine is no longer a dream;
我的梦想不再是梦想；
it's a goal.
它是个目标。
We're going to do this wider and wider,
我们要做得越来越广，
bigger and bigger,
越来越大，
and we're going to know more about the suspect,
我们要了解更多嫌疑人的信息，
and we're going to build an identikit.
我们要建立一个身份证明。
I believe this is also a new era for criminal profiling.
我相信这也是犯罪档案的新时代。
The work of the criminologist
犯罪学家的工作
draws on the expert recognition of behavioral patterns
利用了将过去观察过的行为模式
that have been observed before to belong to a certain type,
归属于特定类型和画像
to a certain profile.
的专家认可。
As opposed to this expert but subjective evaluation,
相对于专家这种主观评估，
we're trying to do the same thing,
我们在试图做同样的事情，
but from the molecular makeup of the fingerprint,
但从指纹的分子结构去看，
and the two can work together.
这两者可以一起工作。
I did say that molecules are storytellers,
我说过分子是讲故事的，
so information on your health,
所以关于你的健康信息，
your actions, your lifestyle, your routines,
你的行为，你的生活形态，你的日常生活，
they're all there,
它们全在那里，
accessible in a fingerprint.
可通过指纹获取。
And molecules are the storytellers of our secrets
只需轻轻触碰，分子是
in just a touch.
我们秘密的说书人。
Thank you.
谢谢
(Audience) Wow.
（观众）哇。
(Applause)
（掌声）